miversität		
w1en		
MASTERARBEIT / MASTER THESIS		
Titel der Masterarbeit / Title of the Master Thesis		
The emerging Disability Rights Movement		
and the place of intellectual disability		
Verfasser / Author		
Felix Sebastian Balzer		
angestrebter akademischer Grad / academic degree aspired		
Master of Arts (MA)		
"Wien, 2019 / Vienna, 2019"		
Studienkennzahl lt. Studienblatt /		
degree progrannne code as it appears on the student record sheet:		
A 067 805		
Studienrichtung lt. Studienblatt /		
degree progrannne as it appears on the student record sheet:		
Individuelles  Masterstudium:		
Global Studies - A European Perspective		
UNIVERSITÄT		
LEIPZIG		
miversität		
w1en		
MASTERARBEIT / MASTER THESIS		
Titel der Masterarbeit / Title of the Master Thesis		
The emerging Disability Rights Movement		
and the place of intellectual disability		
Verfasser / Author		
Felix Sebastian Balzer		
angestrebter akademischer Grad / academic degree aspired		
Master of Arts (MA)		
"Wien, 2019 / Vienna, 2019"		
Studienkennzahl lt. Studienblatt /		
degree progrannne code as it appears on the student record sheet:		
A 067 805		
Studienrichtung lt. Studienblatt /		
degree progrannne as it appears on the student record sheet:		
Individuelles  Masterstudium:		
Global Studies - A European Perspective		
Abbreviations		
AAIDD		
BCODP CMH CRPD CSDPA DA DIAL DIG DPI DRM GA HRMD ICIDH ICF		
IL ILI		
OHCHR		
UK UN US		
UPIAS RI		
WHO		
American Association on Intellectual and Developmental Disabilities		
British Council of Organizations of Disabled People (*1981) Campaign for people with mental handicaps		
Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities (*2006) Chronically Siek and Disabled Persons Act (* 1970)		
Disability Alliance (* 1974) Disablement Information and Advice Line Disability Income Group (* 1965)		
Disabled People' s International  (* 1981) Disability Rights Movement		
General Assembly of the United Nations Human Rights Model of Disability		
"International Classification oflmpairments, Disabilities and Handicaps (* 1980) International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health (*2001)"		
Independent Living Independent Living Institute		
Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights		
United Kingdom United Nations		
United States of America Union of the Physically Impaired Against Segregation (*1976)		
Rehabilitation International (* 1922 as International Society for Crippled Children)		
World Health Organization		
TABLE OF CONTENT		
1. INTRODUCTION                                                                                                                                   7		
2. RESEARCH SUBJECT AND STRUCTURE                                                                                                        9		
3. OUTLINING DISABILITY                                                                                                                                    12		
3.1. THE CHALLENGE OF DEFINING DISABILITY                                                                                                                  14		
3.2. CLASSIFICATIONS OF DISABILITY                                                                                                                                    17		
3.3. A SOCIAL MODEL OF DISABILITY                                                                                                                                      21		
3.4. NEW SOCIAL MOVEMENT THEORY AND DISABLED PERSONS ÜRGANIZATIONS                                                       22		
4. THE EMERGING DISABILITY RIGHTS MOVEMENT (1960-1981)                                                                  25		
4.1. THE BRITISH DISABILITY MOVEMENT                                                                                                                            28		
4.1.1. The Disability Jncome Group and Disability Alli ance                                                                      29		
4.1.2. Union of the Physically lmpaired Against Segregation                                                                      30		
4.1.3. Social oppr ession theory                                                                                                                    32		
4.2. INDEPENDENT LIVING                                                                                                                                                                   34		
4.2.1. Centersfor Indep endent Living                                                                                                          37		
4.2.2. Minority Group Rights                                                                                                                         37		
4.2.3. Self-advocacy movement                                                                                                                     38		
4.3. DISABLED PEOPLE 'S INTERNATIONAL                                                                                                                    41		
5. ALIGNMENTS OF THE EMERGING DISABILITY RIGHTS MOVEMENT (1960-1981)                                    43		
5.1. COMMONALITIES                                                                                                                                                                   44		
5.2. VARIETY                                                                                                                                                                                   45		
5.2.1. The movement of persons withphysical disabilities                                                                          47		
5.2.2. The movement of persons with intellectual disabilities                                                                     48		
6. THE DISABILITY RIGHTS MOVEMENT AND INTELLECTUAL DISABILITY                                                 51		
6.1. THE ROLE OF THE SOCIAL MODEL OF DISABILITY                                                                                                      52		
6.2. AN INCLUSIVE SOCIAL MODEL OF DISABILITY                                                                                                            55		
6.3. FROM DISABILITY RIGHTS TO THE HUMAN RIGHTS MODEL OF DISABILITY                                                               58		
7. CONCLUSION                                                                                                                                                    65		
8. BIBLIOGRAPHY                                                                                                                                                 69		
9. OTHER SOURCES                                                                                                                                             76		
10. FIGURES                                                                                                                                                           77		
1. Introduction		
The existence of the phenomenon of disability poses questions of commonality and difference.		
"The way societies have treated issues associated with disability is often interconnected with the question of who is regarded as a member of society and who is not. The categories of inclusion and exclusion reflect this and are capable of framing social bonds that are either constructed and emphasized or dissolved. Each society (and, in a broader sense, each culture) has its own way of integrating or excluding certain categories or certain subjects, that is, by creating social links or denying them (Ravaud and Stiker 2001)."		
Processes that constitute inclusionary or exclusionary practices are particularly relevant for persons with disabilities and especially the activities and demands of the Disability Rights Movement (DRM). Especially the beginning of the movement stands exemplary for the effort to create social links for persons with disabilities. The DRM was comprised of persons with disabilities who started to organize on national and transnational levels in the 1960s when similar notions of resistance were translated into political  demands. These demands centered on the living conditions of persons with disabilities in their societies and were brought forward		
in different manners.		
"In this thesis, I aim at identifying these different manners by collating differing strands of the"		
"DRM and by subsuming notions of alignments of the movements, which were part of this ""resistance"" (Gabel and Peters 2004). The complication of the famous slogan of the DRM ""Nothing about us without us"" stands paradigmatic for my research interest (Charlton 1998, 3). By asking, who the 'us' is in the catchy motto of the movement I want to examine the composition of the emerging DRM (ibid. 3)."		
"The early phase of the DRM, which (in my analysis) has taken place in the years 1960-1981 stands paradigmatic for the development of the movement. Highlighting the pioneering processes staged in this time frame will reveal essential aspects of a movement, that was aiming at similar goals but was not as unified, as the central slogan of the movement ""Nothing about"		
"us without us"" insinuates."		
"Building on a refined analysis of the emerging DRM, I will investigate if and how persons with"		
intellectual disabilities or organizations concerned with representing persons with intellectual disabilities were actively involved in the movement. I will depict possible differences between several definitions of disability and aims of the actors that have shaped the movement. In doing		
"so, I want to examine in how far the emerging DRM has held a coherent definition of who"		
qualifies as a 'person with a disability'  or a 'disabled person'  (the two most commonly used		
terms for members of the movement).		
"Has the difference between intellectual and physical disability played a role in the constituting processes of the central organizations of the emerging DRM and if yes, how has this difference been depicted in primary sources and secondary literature?"		
"In retracing such questions  of difference, I want to contribute towards an understanding of disability that might be of relevance for the most common form to which political 'issues of persons with disabilities' were translated in the 21st century: The Disability-Rights-model. This model  was the institutional  answer to the pressure  created  by the DRM (post its emerging"		
phase).		
The rise of this movement entailed a politicization of the matter that has changed the conception		
"of disability and disabled persons on many different levels. Most 'gains' of the DRM have been translated into rights questions. This can be seen in the clearest reference to disability rights in an international human rights treaty, the adoption of the Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities (CRPD) by the general assembly of the United Nations in 2006. This treaty has proclaimed the rights of persons with disabilities as Human Rights on an equal level with all other humans. The main 'interlocutor' to advocate the newly emerging view of disability,"		
that has also been at the base of the CRPD was the social model of disability.		
I will take this fact as an incentive to further analyze and exceed the scope of the emerging		
"DRM (1960-1981) by examining whether persons with intellectual  disabilities  were referenced in this model. In how far has the social model of disability addressed persons with intellectual disabilities? How could a model  look, that is including persons with intellectual disabilities? Following these questions, understood as imperatives, I will discuss whether the ""Human Rights Model of Disability"" that claims to deliver the most refined definition of disability nowadays (Degener 2014) has reflected this issue."		
"By firstly depicting a prologue of the emerging DRM I will offer insights on the development from the disability movement to the 'new social movement' DRM. In doing so, a foundation of the understandings of disability, resting on different tenets will be outlined. This will contribute to a refined understanding of the 'place' persons with intellectual disabilities take within the emerging DRM but also in more contemporary settings, such as the CRPD. This examination offers important insights to assess the processes that have led to forms of inclusion or exclusion"		
of persons with an intellectual disability.		
2. Research subject and structure		
The research  objective  of this thesis  is a depiction  of the  constituting  processes  from  the		
beginnings of the disability movement to the DRM from  1960-1981. This time frame will be termed  the  emerging  DRM  and  references  the  initial  formation  processes  that  shaped  the		
movement.		
"In depicting the movements' actors and tenets, in the emerging phase of the DRM, defined here"		
"as the  period of 1960-1981, questions of the  condition of the 'momentum' that  has led to political commitments for the cause of rights for persons with disabilities shall be examined in this thesis. This 'momentum' is situated in a time frame, which has constituted the emerging DRM. lt falls into a period that made it possible for initiatives to exert political demands that opposed the predominant form of encountering questions of disability: the 'individual' or 'medical model of disability'. Such encounters with persons with disabilities were recognized by the emerging DRM and interpreted as producing social contexts, in which persons with disabilities found themselves mostly confronting charity and pity. I will trace these supposedly unorganized 'moments of resistance' against conventional forms of placing persons with disabilities in such contexts. Thus, focusing on the emergence of a movement that is closely"		
associated with its resistance against the politics of disablement (Michael Oliver 1990).		
The examination will be undertaken by analyzing records in literature and primary sources of		
"national history records and references of an international organization. This decision has been caused by pragmatic reasoning, as the two national cases of an emerging DRM have been well documented in the United Kingdom and the United States. Therefore, the scope of the research will  be limited to the boundaries  of two nation  states and the example  of the international"		
organization.		
The status and depiction of emerging formations of organized protest against existing disability		
"policies in other countries is also of great interest and would have to include the ""subversive status"" of issues concerning disability, as it has been called for the status of Disability Studies in Germany, Austria and Switzerland (Pfahl and Powell 2014).  However, the limited scope of"		
this thesis does not leave room to extend the examination in this direction.		
"A critique of most disability movements and the argument, that most movements neglect the"		
question of race and gender is brought forward by Ayesha Vernon on The Dialectics of multiple Identities and the disabled peoples  movement (1999). In a similar manner I want to depict		
intellectual disability as a submerged field within Disability  Studies this thesis: by employing		
"existing literature of the academic discipline, which is generally referred to as Disability Studies, the emerging phase of the DRM shall be contextualized. This examination will be set in this time frame, as rights for persons with disabilities were yet a distant demand of a small number of disability rights activists that only gradually started to engage in the field of ""the politics of disability"" (Mike Oliver 1984). Rachel Hurst even claims that ""no organized DRM, either at the international  level or at the national  level has existed"" (2003, 572). Before the"		
emerging phase of the DRM (1960- 1981).		
"However, the 201"		
"century has been rich in different stances towards disability. These stances,"		
the resistance against these stances and what this has caused will be of interest for this thesis.		
I have chosen to frame the issues concerning disability by examining one particular aspect within the time frame of 1960-1981. This aspect concerns the depiction and representation of intellectual disability within the emerging DRM on national and international levels.		
Has the difference between intellectual and physical disability played a role in the constituting		
"processes of the central organizations of the emerging DRM and if yes, how has this difference been depicted?"		
"To answer this research question, it has been a necessary step to include accessible sources and"		
"to consult records of institutions where 'the' emerging DRM can be located. These locations are the Disability-Archive established by the University of Leeds and the online library of the Independent Living Institute as a source for documents that have collated records of the DRM in its emerging phase. In addition, this thesis understands itself as a contribution to revelations of different historical and cultural facets of inclusion and exclusion."		
"This means that it is necessmy to determine who is affected by exclusion and inclusion, determine what disabled persons are excluded from or what they are included in, and how and to what degree they are in or out at different times and in different social groupings (Ravaud and Stiker 2001, 490)."		
The examination will lead to a discussion on how actors of the emerging DRM have treated the		
matter of intellectual disability in their emerging phase and how this affected the process of 'establishing ' rights for persons with intellectual disabilities.		
"In this manner, the depiction of movements of the DRM shall contextualize the main actors and tenets, which describe the focal points of these actors involved. The identification of these tenets is useful to shed a light on certain contingencies and general assumptions concerning the issue. Through the depiction of the tenets, the relevant discourse positions of the relation of"		
physical  and intellectual  disability will be discussed. The term  'Discourse' has evolved as a		
stable companion of the vocabulary  of the humanities over the past decades. The concept is		
capable of illustrating a wide range of issues and has been subject to a large number of usages in the social sciences:		
"[...] discourse means anything from a historical monument, a lieu de memoire , a policy , a political strategy, narratives in a restricted or broad sense of the term, text, talk, a speech, topic-related conversations, to language per se. [...] thus stretching the meaning of discourse from a genre to a register or style, from a building to a political program (Wodak and Meyer 2009, 18)."		
"By embedding the discourse of this thesis, Critical Discourse Analysis (CDA) will be utilized."		
"This will help to identify manifestations of intellectual disability as expressions and depictions of certain negotiation processes of a social phenomenon, trying to explain its genesis and structure. The arrangement of statements is not only a collection of sentences and texts but a chain of statements, which lets the reader understand the context. What qualifies as a chain of statements? Michel Foucault, who has been one of the first social researchers to deploy work in such terms, proposes to treat discourse analysis as a 'toolbox' that helps to research patterns and hidden rules of how language is used, and which narratives are created. In a later publication, he extended his understanding of discourse by stating that:"		
"[...] a discourse is not a slender surface of contact, or confrontation, between a reality and a language (langue), the intrication of a lexicon and an experience ; 1would like to show with precise examples that in analyzing discourses themselves, one sees the loosening of the embrace, apparently so tight, of worlds and things, and the emergence of a group of mles proper to discursive practice (Foucault 1971, 22)."		
"The tenets of the DRM' s strands are composed by combining statements of the movements,"		
"that were part of the emerging DRM. Contemporary publications have picked up the  important contribution, that discourse analysis plays for an analysis of the historical trajectory of disability. One example points out the prospects of discourse analysis in the context of theorizing about disability in stressing a certain congruency:"		
"With asymmetric power relations, with marginalization and discrimination, and with the way in which the social categories that reproduce and reinforce these phenomena come into being. [...] discourse analysis can show how the current models grew out of different discourses, and provide an outside"		
"perspective on the potential for integrating them (Gme 2011, 534)."		
"lt is not possible, however, to cover the discourse in its entirety. As a researcher doing critical"		
"discourse analysis, due to the character of discourse itself 1, therefore, have to make a distinct choice of which subject exactly, which strand of the discourse and which participants of that strand 1want to analyze. The basis of CDA includes a literature review of the most important actors of the DRM, in order to identify the actors and tenets of the various strands of the DRM. By deploying these 'strands', the general alignments of these strands will be analyzed according"		
to their alignment in regard to their definition of disability.		
In further tracing the ways in which intellectual disability has been defined within the emerging		
"DRM, the last chapter convenes recent trends and research in intellectual disability advocacy. Within this last chapter, a discussion of the social model of disability in relation to intellectual disability, possible prospects of an inclusive social model of disability and the Human Rights Model of Disability (HRMD) will be carried out."		
3. Outlining Disability		
There is substantial anthropological and scientific evidence that throughout history people with		
"'recognizable' impairments, who would today be considered 'disabled', have existed in relatively large numbers in all societies across the world. lt is also quite evident that societal responses to impairment and disability are historically,  culturally and geographically variable"		
"(Ingstad and Whyte, as cited in Barnes 2003)."		
"The sentence: ""Disability is an enigma that we experience but do not necessarily understand"""		
"(Albrecht, Seelman, and Bury 2001, 1) describes prevalent receptions of disability in most present societies, which often refer to the phenomenon of disability as a problem. How is a problem solved? Usually by treating this ""enigma"" as the problem and by accumulating hints to decipher it (ibid. 1). The hints are often diagnosed  as deviance, as ""humans have always tended to create techniques to measure forms of deviance: from Hippocratic humoral pathology to contemporary endeavors of cataloging genomic sequences"" (Fujiura and Rutkowski-Kmitta"		
"2001, 69)."		
Why do we do so? An easy answer is not to be formulated within this thesis. But naming this		
"section 'defining disability' aims at retracing references of the process of conceiving some of the 'deviance-techniques'. By reflecting the ways in which disability has been defined and by pointing out core questions of definition, it is intended to give an overview of the ordering mechanisms that persons with disabilities have been and still are subject of."		
"Looking at these defining instruments of disability, it is necessary to bear in mind that ""several exist and serves specific purposes in different systems of order and have to be fit to purpose"" (Fujiura and Rutkowski-Kmitta 2001, 78). This is specifically observable in 19th century Europe when many medical and statistical techniques were 'discovered'. An appropriate case, which exemplifies this tendency is the 'exploration' of the antagonist of deviance: the norm."		
The idea of 'the norm' is connected with the development of statistics and was facilitated by		
"the equation of the bell curve, also called the normal curve. In this paradigm, the majority of"		
bodies fall under the main umbrella of the normal curve. Those that do not are at its limits and		
"are regarded as statistically a-normal. Connected with definite ideas, what society should 'look like', an imperative was placed  on people to conform, to fit in, under the rubric of normality (Davis 2002). Subsequently, this normalizing logic has been expanded to analyze the human mind and varying ideas of the intellect. In coining terms such as 'mental illness', definite stances for the evaluation of such phenomena were given. These phenomena are subsumed in this thesis by the designation 'intellectual disability', that is of special interest for this thesis. But before I turn towards this term, the next section will provide an important distinction, often"		
utilized when defining disability.		
One of the underlying questions of what constitutes disability is the evaluation of the effects of		
"impairments. The distinction generated out of this contrast is situated at the  intersection between the particular needs of a person's impairment, the social interpretation of this impairment and the larger political and economic context of disability. The process of categorizing impairments is based on the distinction of disability and impairment: ""Disability constitutes itself, within a larger social context, while impairment is a biological condition"" (Braddock and Parrish 2001, 12). However, the outcome of these reflections often has led to the establishment of categories and questions such as who is to be included in these 'categories of impairment'. This categorization thus fosters the stereotyping of disabled persons. Since few non-disabled  people in the 'majority-society'  interact directly with persons with  disabilities,"		
they rely heavily on stereotypes in their response to persons with disabilities (Munyi 2012).		
The categorization  of persons with disabilities is thus not capable of taking into account the		
"difference among disabled persons. Jerome Bickenbach, who has been involved in the drafts of several publications relating to concepts of disability stresses, the importance of recognizing the differences of the various conceptions of disability. He points out that the overall debate about a definite, correct scientific definition of disability is ultimately misguided, especially in social sciences: ""More than a single definition is needed to understand disability"" (Bickenbach 2012, 68). Definitions are usually used to understand phenomena and as Jerome Bickenbach points out a global definition of disability that fits all circumstances is in reality nearly impossible. In the following chapter, I will treat the arising difficulties that come with the aim"		
of defining disability.		
3.1. The challenge of defining disability		
lt has been observed that there is no neutral language with which to discuss disability (Williams		
"1996; Zola 1993; Linton 1998, as cited in Altman 2001), and yet the ""tainted language itself and the categories used to influence the definition of the problem"" (Williams 1996, as cited in Altmann 2001, 97). The difficulty to define disability is rooted in the fact that disability is a"		
"complicated, multidimensional  concept."		
"Since the early  1960s, there have been various attempts to provide  and develop conceptual"		
"schemata to describe and explain the complex relationships between illness, impairment, disability, and handicap. This has led to various different attempts of defining disability, as Barnes and Mercer (1996) point out. But the universality of the phenomenon of disability should neither be conflated with what counts as a disability nor with its causes. The statement ""disability takes many forms and thus resists universalization"" sums up a central 'problem' of the 'disability contradiction' (Dryden 2013,  1). Describing these  'many forms' is a challenge in itself, as the range of different forms of disability varies tremendously, as has been also stated in the World Report on disability, by the World Health Organization (WHO):"		
"Persons with disabilities are diverse and heterogeneous , while stereotypical views of disability emphasize"		
"wheelchair users and a few other ""classic"" groups such as blind people and deaf people. Disability encompasses the child bom with a congenital condition such as cerebral palsy or the young soldier who loses his leg to a land-mine, or the middle-aged woman with severe arthritis, or the older person with dementia, among many others. (Y'/ orld Health Organization 2011, 7)."		
Taking into account an international comparison of survey data on disability also reveals how		
"differently the status of disability is categorized. An example of this problem can be found in the divergence of statistics. The official worldwide share of disabled persons in the  total population varies widely as exemplified in figures of the World Report on Disability. 1 have chosen the two countries with the greatest disparity of the total amount of persons with disabilities: ""Between 0.8% in the Syrian Arab Republic and 33% (city) and 39% (country) in"		
"Norway  (1991)"" (ibid.)."		
Despite  the  non-existence  of  a universal  definition  of  disabilities  as a consequence  of the		
"enormous variety of disabilities, the depiction of disability in most Western societies is a quite monolithic and stereotypical one. The perception of disability in these countries has often been associated with ""images of wheelchairs, crutches, guide dogs, and so on. Maya Sabatello and Marianne  Schulze diagnose this with a particular view onto disability that is concerned with"		
"""western obsession with  scientific explanation""  (Sabatello  and  Schulz 2014,  18). They  also"		
"point  to the explanation  of   ""other cultures""  for disability  by  stating that these  approaches"		
"include a range of sources, particularly religious beliefs about one' s sins, demand for collective restitution, imbalance in one' s own and the communal cosmos (ibid. 18)."		
"There is a general consensus that within Western culture, there is a discernable cultural bias against people with any form of perceived biological 'abnormality' or 'flaw' that can be traced back to the ancient world of the Greeks and Romans (Garland 1995). The most apparent separation that serves this 'western obsession' has caused is a differentiation of physical and intellectual disability. The constitution of physical disability often rests on a distinction of phenomenological,  e.g. 'visible' otherness, whereas intellectual disabilities cannot be captured"		
and determined  as 'simple'.		
"The umbrella  term  ""developmental  disability""  is utilized  by  the  American  Association  on"		
Intellectual and Developmental Disability (AAIDD) to include many forms of disabilities:		
"lt includes people with severe chronic disabilities that can be cognitive or physical or both. These disabilities appear before the age of 22 and are likely to be lifelong. Some developmental disabilities stem from physical issues, such as cerebral palsy or epilepsy. Some individuals may have a condition that includes a physical and intellectual disability, for example, Down syndrome or fetal alcohol syndrome (Schalock et al. 2010, 22)."		
"The term is rooted in a functional rather than a moral model (Carey 2009, 14). This is generally"		
"reflected in the approach western society tends to have towards disability, where the physical observation of bodily limitation has been a focal point in defining disability."		
"However, when cognitive limitations are referenced, the term Intellectual disability is usually utilized. How intellectual disability fits within the general construct of disability is part of ongoing discussions, that take place in competing worldviews within the conceptualization of the phenomenon disability. Formulations formerly used, are ""idiot, imbecile, feeble-minded , mentally subnormal, moron, and retard"" (Switzky and Greenspan 2006, 15). Denominations now seen as highly pejorative and stigmatizing. Organizations have responded to community pressure to use more acceptable language - which itself is subject to change over time (Parmenter 2001, 284). The AAIDD, who has also coined the term developmental disabilities, as described above has been central in these renaming efforts. This shows in the AAIDD's efforts to change the term from the formerly used 'mental retardation' to 'intellectual disability'. In 1992 the association defined ""mental retardation"" as ""involving significant impairment in intellectual functioning with significant impairment of at least two areas of adaptive functioning and age of onset  before 18 years"" (American Association on Mental Retardation  1992, 5). lt is important to note that this definition of mental retardation in 1992"		
was the first one to view the term as a condition that could be enhanced by the provision  of		
"supports,  rather than  as a static, lifelong  disability.  The Association  has worked  to further"		
develop and refine this term. This has led to a renaming by a 'minor edit' that substitutes the term intellectual disability for mental retardation in 2002:		
"Intellectual disability is characterized by significant limitations both in intellectual functioning and in adaptive behavior  as expressed in conceptual, social, and practical adaptive skills. This disability originates before the age of 18. Assumptions are an explicit part of the definition because they clarify the context from which the definition arises and indicate how the definition must be applied. Thus, the definition of intellectual disability cannot stand alone. The following five assumptions are essential to the application of the definition of intellectual disability."		
1. Limitations in present functioning must be considered within the context of community environments		
typical of the individual's age peers and culture.		
"2. Valid assessment considers cultural and linguistic diversity as well as differences in communication, sensory, motor, and behavioral factors."		
"3. Within an individual, limitations often coexist with strengths."		
4. An important purpose of describing limitations is to develop a profile of needed supports.		
"5. With appropriate personalized supports over a sustained period, the life functioning of the person with intellectual disability generally will improve (Schalock et al. 2007, 118)."		
The approach of shifting the paradigm  surrounding the term is more fully fleshed out in the		
"Association's 1lth and most recent manual, Intellectual Disability: Definition, Classification, and Systems of Supports. Robert Schalock commented on the shift as having the following benefits:"		
"The term intellectual disability (a) reflects the changed constmct of disability proposed by AAIDD and WHO; (b) aligns better with current professional practices that are focused on functional behaviors and contextual factors; (c) provides a logical basis for individualized supports provision due to its basis in a social--ecological framework; (d) is less offensive to persons with disabilities ; and (e) is more consistent with international terminology (Schalock 2007, 120)."		
"For this thesis,  1 will  concentrate  on the term intellectual  disability. The difference between"		
"intellectual disability and a mental health condition is a case that needs such a differentiation. The two phenomena are often confused. Mental illness is an illness and may be cured, whereas intellectual disability is a life-long condition. People with intellectual disability are not ill unless they have a common illness. They need easy-to-understand information, education or training to live included in society (Gentile, Manetta, and Jackson 2013, 413). The difficulties of finding a common ground of definitions and the manifold definitions that exist have led to classifications and different conceptions of disability. This classification of disability has itself been viewed  as a problem;  on the one side needed,  but often connected  with paternalizing"		
aspects of social policies (Shakespeare  1996).		
"Nonetheless,  1 will  depict  the most  important  classifications  of  disability  in the following"		
chapter to depict the contexts(s) in which the attempts of defining disability have to be situated.		
3.2. Classifications of disability		
Modem societies most commonly seek ways to deal with disabled persons by adopting models		
"of disability, proposed by experts. A model is a theoretical construction a priori and not an empirical generalization - it is a structure that usually brings different components into meaningful contexts and thus helps to understand complex phenomena such as disability. Conceptualization in this sense is not in itself true or false  - it can only be more or less appropriate, helpful or consistent (Bickenbach 2013, 53). The model versions are used to illustrate the different conceptions of disability and are intended as conceptual  starting points"		
for the development of perspectives of complex phenomena with the imperative of using them.		
"If sociologists had an interest in the sociology of disability, it was somewhat submerged in"		
"studies of stigma and stigmatization. The academic field ""Symbolic interactionism"" that Erving Goffman (1964) was also associated with, developed an array of useful concepts around the idea of ""discredited"" and ""discreditable"" identities and studied the management of the interaction between ""normal"" and the chronically sick and disabled. In a similar fashion, disability in medical sociology has not been a major research interest. Studies of disability typically appeared in research on aging, where it was represented under the heading of ""dependency"". In this setting, disability became associated with negative ""images of ageing"""		
"(Turner 2001, 252)."		
"This chapter is comprised of the main ways to classify disability, that is the individual/medical"		
"model of disability, most fit for classification of disability. Historically, people with all kinds of impairments were viewed as socially inadequate and systematically excluded from  all manner of economic and social activity. Since the nineteenth century, their interests were increasingly represented by cadres of disability professionals and professionally led impairment-specific organizations that perpetuated an individual medical view of disablement. This medical model of disability is mainly reflected in the discipline of medical sociology. Herein, medical diagnoses play a central role and are the main form of analysis for the categorization of disability. The 'problem of disability' is expected to be solved by adapting the individual to his or her environment. lt asks, to what extent physical or intellectual 'defects' are present, and the subsequent focus of on malfunctions in 'performance'  as a result of these"		
defects. This rather simple but efficient derivation of disability is shown in Figure 1.		
"FIGURE 1: A MEDICAL MODEL OF DISABILITY
,'
,'"		
"individual's physical or mental trait (e.g., a gene associated with deafness)"		
"individual's functional impairment
(e.g., inability to hear)"		
"individual's  disadvantage (e.g., economic, social, political status)"		
"Figure  1. A Medical Model of Disability. Reprinted from M. Samaha, Adam M. 2007. ""What Good Is the Social"		
"Model of Disability?"" SSRN Scholarly Paper (Rochester, NY:  Social Science Research Network.):  74."		
This form of assessment of disability has been very influential in creating tools. One tool that		
"needs to be mentioned is the classifications of the World Health Organization (WHO). The organization has established disability classifications as measurement methods, which function as derivates of the medical model of disability with a logic of standard and deviation. The first version of the 'tool' is the International Classification of Impairments, Disabilities and Handicaps (ICIDH), which was first published in 1980. This WHO directive was intended to stress a theretofore insufficient understanding of disease. The ICIDH criticized, among other issues, that a purely pathological diagnosis of a disease offers an insufficient general medical perspective on the health status of individuals. As a result of this reorientation of theoretical­ medical practice, a new definition of the concept of disability was established (Rosenbaum and Stewart 2004, 4). For the first time, the distinctions between damage (impairment), disability and handicap were included:"		
"(a) Impairments , concemed with abnormalities of body stmcture and appearance and with organ or system function) resulting from any cause; in principle, impairments represent disturbances at the organ level."		
"(b) Disabilities, reflecting the consequences of impairment in terms of functional performance and activity by the individual; disabilities thus represent disturbances at the level of the person."		
"(c) Handicaps, concemed with the disadvantages experienced by the individual as a result of impairments and disabilities; handicaps thus reflect interaction with and adaptation to the individual's surroundings (World Health Organization 1980, 14)."		
"As a result of this of this classification, the WHO was criticized at length for the utilized terms,"		
"which held negative connotations. The orientation of the classification was too focused on the medical context, and that the living circumstances of the persons, which were 'affected' could not be described with sufficient accuracy. This is also referenced in the applicational aspects of the model:"		
"Most problems concemed the nature of the relationship between disability and handicap and the distinction between these concepts. Perhaps the cmx of this difficulty is that handicap may be seen as being a direct consequence of impairment and disability. That the relationship between these two aspects cannot be easily defined is a thread of concem which mns through many of the papers. These concems have in common the need to build more social and environmental elements into the model (Badley 1987, 122)."		
The criticism was 'handled' by the WHO through adjustments that resulted in the International		
"Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health (ICF) in 2001. This new  classification formally replaced the ICIDH and an expanded its definition of disability, as the organization put forward, the components of the model offer a ""biopsychosocial perspective"" on health (World Health Organization 2001, 4). Furthermore, the authors of the model claim that the ICF is a ""classification of the consequences of disease towards a classification of the disease components of health and takes with respect to the etiology of a neutral point of view and emphasizes functional health"" (ibid, 4). The term handicap, which was a key term in the ICIDH was abandoned because the term is linked with derogatory connotations. In addition, the terms injury and impairment or malfunction are summarized as an impairment. Disability is now considered an umbrella term for limitations  in social participation opportunities as well as expressing social discrimination due to an impairment. And it further constitutes, a ""complex dimension and potential social disadvantage manifests itself in various forms and is influenced by a variety of intervening factors"" (World Health Organization 2001, 28):"		
"Body functions are the physiological functions of body systems (including psychological functions). Body stmctures are anatomical parts of the body such as organs, limbs and their components. Impairments are problems in body function or stmcture such as a significant deviation or loss. Activity is the execution of a task or action by an individual. Participation is involvement in a life situation. Activity limitations are difficulties an individual may have in executing activities. Participation restrictions are problems an individual may experience in involvement in life situations. Environmental factors make up the physical, social and attitudinal environment in which people live and conduct their lives (World Health Organization 2001, 10)."		
Health Condition		
(disorder or disease)		
Body Functions		
A                                                                                                                                 ·		
i         i		
Personal Factors		
Environmental Factors		
Contextual Factors		
"Figure 2. The International Classification of Function, Disability and Health (ICF). Figure reprinted from World"		
"Health Organization. 2001. ""The International Classification of Function, Disability and Health (ICF)."" Geneva, Switzerland: 18."		
Scholars and activists have rejected the assumptions which underpin the models and questioned		
the adequacy of  them as a sufficient basis for empirical work (Mike Oliver 2017). This resistance can be traced back to the 1970s when research of the application of the medical model of disability and the consequences of the model for persons with disabilities began.		
"One  of the  criticisms,  that  exemplifies  the  critique  is one that  frames  disabled  persons  as"		
"""socially dysfunctional"" in such a model. The A life apart: A pilot study of residential institutions for the physically handicapped and the young chronic sick, set out to examine the effects of the medical model for persons with disabilities and concluded with the rather extreme diagnosis that ""in a medical model of disability, persons with disabilities are socially dead"" (Miller and Gwynne 1972, 80). In the following chapter we will take a closer look at how this resistance has emerged and which difference facets played a role in formulating central ideas"		
of this resistance against the medical model of disability.		
