miversität w1en
MASTERARBEIT I MASTER'S THESIS
Titel der Masterarbeit I Title of the Master's Thesis
Security Seetor Reform in the State-Building Process in Afghanistan
verfasst von / submitted by
Almira Abdulsatarova BA
angestrebter akademischer Grad / in partial fulfilment of the requirements for the degree of
Master of Arts (MA)
"Wien, 2019 I Vienna 2019"
Studienkennzahl lt. Studienblatt /
degree programme code as it appears on the student record sheet:
A 066 824
Studienrichtung lt. Studienblatt /
degree programme as it appears on the student record sheet:
Plitikwissenschaft
Betreut von / Supervisor:                                             Univ.-Prof. Dr. Otmar Höll
ABSTRACT
In the light  of growing  recognition  that  an effective  and  professional  security  sector  can
"drive peace and promote sustainable development , the security sector reform has been at the forefront of the international donor community for the last two decades. At the heart of the concept lies the notion of human security that focuses on fostering the culture of human rights and the rule of law, as well as on strengthening the resilience of security and justice sectors to emerging vulnerabilities and threats. Since the concept became the critical element of the prevention and sustaining peace agendas, it has been translated into numerous peace missions around the world. However, peace and security stakeholders have faced substantial challenges to the practical implementation of reforms in conflict-affected  environments, where füll alignment with security sector reform's core principles and norms has not been achieved. This paper provides both theoretical knowledge and practical experience on security sector reform with a view to investigate the reasons behind poor performance of donor-driven development programs. The Afghan example represents the most expensive, largest and longest-running reconstruction and state-building mission of all times but it also perfectly illustrates the gravity of donors' failure to actualise holistic, people-centred and context-specific  development  assistance,  resulting  in  ongoing  violence  and  suffering  in"
Afghanistan.
ZUSAMMENFASSUNG
"Im   Lichte   der   wachsenden    Anerkennung ,   dass   em   effektiver   und    professioneller"
"Sicherheitssektor den Friedensprozess vorantreiben  und  eine   nachhaltige  Entwicklung fördern kann, ist die Sicherheitssektorreform im Vordergrund der internationalen Spendergemeinschaft seit den letzten zwei Jahrzehnten gewesen. Im  Mittelpunkt  des Konzepts steht der Begriff der menschlichen Sicherheit, das sich darauf konzentriert , die Kultur der Menschenrechte und der Rechtsstaatlichkeit zu fördern, sowie auch die Widerstandsfähigkeit des Sicherheits- und Justizsektors gegenüber aufkommenden Schwachstellen und Bedrohungen zu stärken. Da das Konzept ein kritisches Element der Prävention- und Friedenagenden wurde, setzte man es in zahlreichen Friedensmissionen auf der ganzen Welt um. Friedens- und Sicherheitsakteure standen jedoch vor erheblichen Herausforderungen bei der praktischen Umsetzung von Reformen in konfliktbetroffenen Ländern, in denen keine vollständige Angleichung an die Grundprinzipien und Normen der Sicherheitssektorreform erreicht wurde. Dieser  Text bietet  sowohl theoretische  Kenntnisse als auch praktische Erfahrungen auf dem Gebiet der Sicherheitssektorreform , in der Absicht, die Gründe hinter der schwachen Leistung von den Gebern betriebenen Entwicklungsprogrammen zu untersuchen. Das afghanische Beispiel vertritt die  teuerste, größte und am längsten laufende Rekonstruktions- und Staatsbildungsmission aller Zeiten, es beschreibt auch vollkommen die Schwere des Misserfolgs von Gebern, eine holistische , am Menschen   orientierte   und   kontextspezifische   Entwicklungshilfe   zu   verwirklichen ,   die"
dadurch die anhaltende Gewalt und Not in Afghanistan verursacht.
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS
"This research would not have been possible without Andrea Mancini , who took a chance on"
"me and introduced to the world of the United Nations. Andrea provided me with both enriching experience that truly has the potential to impact my life and an incentive to write this thesis on security sector reform topic. 1 am greatly indebted to him for all support, encouragement  and  guidance throughout  my priceless  time with the Regional  Section for"
West and Central Asia.
"At Vienna University , 1 would like to express sincere gratitude to my supervisor, Professor"
"Otmar  Höll,  for  giving  me  the  freedom  to  develop  this  research  the  way  1 see  it,  for providing me with insights and advises in most comprehensive manner possible, as well as"
for devoting his time and energy on my intellectual development.
"My  very  special  thanks  go to  my  dear  friends,  Arbena  Arifi  and  Emre  Poyrazoglu ,  for"
support that 1needed in various times of my life in Vienna and for joining me in joy through the highs and tears through the downs.
"Last, but not least, 1 would like to thank my family. My parents, Alfya and Farid, for their"
"endless love, encouragement and faith in me. My sister and brother-in-law , Alisa and Hagen, for being  part  of my foundation  in Vienna  and  providing  me with  a sense  of resilience."
"Finally, this research is dedicated to my grandparents, who always applaud my successes."
CONTENTS
INTRODUCTION                                                                                                                          8
Chapter 1.  Security-development discourse after the end of Cold War: roots of security sector reform                                                                                                                                 12
1.   Redefinition of security: from realism to human security ....„ ......„ ......„ ......„ ......„       13
1.1.     Realist school of thought                                                                                             13
1.2.      Barry Buzan and widening of security agenda                                                           15
1.3.      Critical security studies and shifting to individual security                                      17
1.4.     Human security                                                                                                            18
2.   Redefinition of development ..........„ ......„ ......„ ......„ ......„ ......„ ......„ ......„ ......„ ......„      21
3.    The Liberal Peace of 1990s                                                                                                  24
4.    Post-conflict peacebuilding                                                                                                  26
Chapter 2.  Security sector reform as a part of statebuilding paradigm: addressing the challenges of fragility                                                                                                                   30
1.    The concept of state fragility                                                                                                30
1.1.     Defining state failure                                                                                                   30
1.2.     Effects of state failure                                                                                                  33
2.    Statebuilding as a response to fragility                                                                                36
Chapter 3.  Security sector reform: evolution of the concept and its core principles              42
1.    Historical development of the security sector reform concept                                          42
2.    SSR basic terms and principles                                                                                            46
Chapter 4.  Historical processes of state formation in Afghanistan since the 18th century . .. 54 Chapter 5.  Security sector reform in Afghanistan                                                                     65
1.    Military reform                                                                                                                      67
1.1.      The Mini stry of Defense professi onalisation                                                            73
2.  Police reform .................................................................. „ ......„ ......„ ......„ ......„ ......„    75
2.1.      The Ministry of Interior professionalisation                                                               84
3.    Judicial reform                                                                                                                      86
4.    Countemarcotics ....„ ......„ ......„ ......„ ......„ ......„ ......„ ......„ ......„ ......„ ......„ ......„ ......„         92
CONCLUSION                                                                                                                             97
ANNEX 1                                                                                                                                   103
ANNEX 2                                                                                                                                   105
LIST OF REFERENCES                                                                                                            107
TABLES AND FIGURES
Tables
Table 1: Dimensions of human security according 1994 Human Development Report                                     20
Table 2: Train-and-equip security assistance vs SSR                                                                                                  29
Table 3: Common tasks in peacebuilding and state-building in the post-conflict period                                   39
Table 4: Development agencies' engagement in SSR                                                                                         44
Table 5: Security Seetor Map                                                                                                                                        47
Table 6: SSR Instruments                                                                                                                                              49
"Table 7: The U.S. support to Train and Equip the Afghan Army , 2002-2011 , dollars in millions                     68"
Table 8: Comparing key elements of the Afghan national army                                                                                70
"Table 9: Defense Assessment of ANA Capabilities, as of April 2008                                                                71"
Table 10: German equipment and construction aid for the Afghan police forces                                               77
"Table 11: Total U.S. funding for the ANA, dollars in billions                                                                             78"
Table 12: ANP Capability Assessments                                                                                                                       79
Table 13: ANA and ANP Killed in Action                                                                                                                   80
Table 14: Evolution of ANP Training                                                                                                                  81
"Table 15: The EUPOL mission in Afghanistan: the results summary, 2015                                                              83"
Table 16: Summary of ltaly 's activities under SSR judicial pillar                                                                      88
"Table 17: Judges ' access to legal resources, 2006-2007                                                                               89"
Table 18: Description of key U.S. government justice sector programs in Afghanistan                                    91
"Table 19: Opinions about dispute resolution institutions, 2018, per cent                                                           92"
"Table 20: Confidence in officials, institutions and organisation, per cent                                                          92"
Table 21: U.S. Counternarcotics strategies and objectives for Afghanistan                                                               93
"Table 22: USAID Agricultural Programs, Results!fargets, 2008-2009                                                              95"
Figures
Figure 1: Dimensions of development according to 1994 An Agenda For Development                                         24
Figure 2: Fragile states index heat map                                                                                                                        33
Figure 3: Pillars of SSR in Afghanistan                                                                                                               66
"Figure 4: U.S. troop levels in Afghanistan, 2002-2018                                                                                       72"
Figure 5: Capability milestone rating of MoD: quarterly change                                                                               74
"Figure 6: Monthly ANDSF Assessment Ratings, January and April 2015                                                                82"
"Figure 7: Capability milestone rating of Mol: quarterly change, 2012                                                               85"
"Figure 8: Opium poppy cultivation in Afghanistan, 1994-2018                                                                         96"
ABBREVIA TIONS
ANA
ANDSF ANP DAC DCAF DFID DPA DPKO EUPOL FSI HDI
HDR IASSRTF IDLO ITGN LICUS OECD OHCHR OSAA OSRSVC PBSO SDG SIGAR UNCF UNDFW UNDP UNDP UNITR UNODA UNODC UNOPS UNPF USAID
Afghan National Army
Afghan National Defense and Security Forces Afghan National Police
Development Assistance  Committee
Geneva Centre for the Democratic Control of Armed Forces Department for International Development
Department of Political and Peacebuilding Affairs Department of Peacekeeping  Operations
European Policing Mission to Afghanistan Fragile States Index
Human Development Index Human Development Report Inter-Agency SSR Task Force
International  Development  Law Organisation Integrated Teclmical Guidance Notes
Low-Income Countries Under Stress
Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development
Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights Office of the Special Adviser on Africa
Office of the Special Representative of the Secretary-General on Sexual Violence in Conflict Peacebuilding Support Office
Sustainable Development Goals
Special Inspector General for Afghanistan Reconstruction United Nations Children's Fund
United Nations Development Fund for Women United Nations Development Programme United Nations Development Programme
United Nations Institute for Training and Research United Nations Office for Disarmament Affairs United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime
United Nations Office for Project Services United Nations Population Fund.
US Agency for International Development
INTRODUCTION
The purpose of this paper is to provide a comprehensive research on security sector reform
"as a mechanism of state-building in Afghanistan. lt elaborates on the role  of international donors in facilitating progress towards sustainable peace and  reconciliation ,  stability  and good governance in  the country. The paper reviews development programs and reforms undertaken under security sector reform framework along four main reconstruction lines, namely: (1) military ; (2) police;  (3) judicial ; and (4) counternarcotics. Among other things, the research attempts to deliver a holistic picture on security sector reform as a relatively new concept in security-development  discourse by illustrating its origins and evolution, and"
"analysing its core objectives, capabilities, as well as limitations."
"The theoretical  framework, which underpins this research , is built on security-development"
"nexus paradigm. Security sector reform is unique concept, since it represents the point of convergence of two previously distant areas - security and development. Security has been traditionally conceptualized within the realist tradition focusing on preservation and increase of the state power, while the security assistance to the military and police forces has been a technocratic exercise of training and equipping. The new reality of post-Cold War era has profoundly changed international agenda, shifting the security objective from the state to the well-being of the people and introducing entirely new concepts of good governance, human security and human development. Human being became the highest value of security and effective security sector is to serve as a cornerstone for stability and the rule of law, thus providing an enabling environment for sustainable development. While the concept of security sector reform had emerged only in late 1990s, it was mainstreamed in international development and security assistance discourse and enjoyed widespread  implementation  in weak states and conflict-affected environments ever since. Security sector reform is now recognized as an essential element of peace- and state-building activities that aims to overcome fragility and post-conflict challenges through development of efficient and accountable systems of security and justice. In 2014, the United Nations Security Council affirmed that security sector reform is critical tool for consolidation of peace and stability, for promotion of poverty reduction, rule of law and good governance, for extension of legitimate State authority, and for prevention of countries from relapsing into conflict (S/RES/2151).  Moreover, the  importance  of  efficient  security  sector  governance  is  at the"
"heart of the Sustainable Development Agenda, which stands for promotion  of peaceful  and"
"inclusive societies, provision  of access to justice  for all and building  effective, accountable"
"and inclusive institutions at all levels (UN SDGs, Goal 16)."
The  research  paper  includes  evaluation  and  analysis  of  the  practical  application  of  the
"security sector reform concept, based on experience gained in Afghanistan. The role and place of the Islamic Republic of Afghanistan in the modern history of international relations is determined by the cycle of armed conflicts, security crisis in the form of the Taliban-led insurgency, illicit opium production and trade, as well as interconnected problems of lawlessness , criminality and corruption. The recent situation in Afghanistan is an important example on how a prolonged armed conflict spreads beyond its borders, entailing dire consequences for the neighbouring countries and destabilizing the situation in the region as a whole. Starting with XIX century, Afghanistan has become a buffer state in the geopolitical confrontation between major powers and since then has almost continuously  experienced armed conflicts. Diplomatie games between British and Russian Empires over the countries of Central and Southern Asia have lasted more than 60 years and resulted in series of short­ term wars. Following the Soviet-Afghan War 1979-1989, Afghanistan plunged into decades of chaos caused by  the Taliban's rise to power. Thus, the country of unique history and culture with geo-strategic location along the Silk Road gradually became a complex humanitarian emergency, one of the poorest states with the lowest human development and"
human security rates in the world.
A new phase of the Afghan historical  development  started in 2001 after the United  States
"and NATO-led intervention and overthrow of the Taliban have taken place. One of the first steps towards stabilisation and transition from war to peace became two interlinked processes: disarmament, demobilisation and reintegration of former combatants and security sector reform. The reconstruction process of Afghanistan has already become the most expensive in history. The USA have along invested more than $117 billion for relief and development assistance, while other international donors have appropriated billions more (SIGAR 2017: 69). The aid committed exceeds even the real value of the Marshall Plan, the"
"U.S. recovery programme to the 16 European countries after the World War II, the inflation­ adjusted cost of which amounts to total of $103.4 billion (SAGAR 2014: 4). Despite such enormous expenditures and substantial cash injections, situation in Afghanistan remains unstable: the civil war continues; some provinces  remain under the control  of the Taliban,"
"the  areas  under  opium  poppy  cultivation  are increasing,  and  the  country  is far  off-track"
towards  implementation  of the  Sustainable Development  Goals. These  challenges  create a
"difficult environment for successful post-conflict reconstruction process, but, equally, make Afghanistan a particularly interesting case study for security sector reform  concept. Moreover, Afghanistan is an important example in understanding the complexity of relationships  among various  actors engaged  (local  and  international)  in  state-building  and"
how their interests may shape post-conflict reconstruction process.
"Against  this  background , this  thesis  addresses  three  principle  research  objectives:  (1) to"
examine the origin and evolution of the security sector reform concept; (2) to conduct comprehensive analysis of the activities undertaken under the SSR framework  in Afghanistan;  and  (3) to  evaluate  to  what  extent  the  implemented  security  sector  reform
programs in Afghanistan meet requirements of the orthodox SSR model.
"To address  the main  objectives  of the  research  paper, the  following  research  question  is"
raised:  which  role  does  the  security  sector  reform  play  in  the  state-building  process  in Afghanistan?
A variety  of  available  published  studies  on  security  sector  reform  was  consulted  in the
"course of preparing this  research. Brzoska (2003) had explored various roots of  security sector reform concept in security-development donor discourse and analysed its strength and inconsistencies inherited. Paris (2004; 2010) had examined the role of liberal peace approach to peace- and state-building agenda of 1990s, from which SSR has evolved. The most comprehensive and holistic study on SSR is provided by Sedra (2017) who has evaluated the SSR prospects in conflict-affected environments. The available published information was supplemented by official documentation of the United Nations, the Department for International Development and the World Bank. The empirical part of the research is based largely on a review of reports published by the Office of the Special Inspector General for Afghanistan Reconstruction , which provides independent and objective oversight of reform activities in the country, and by the United States Government Accountability Office. From this point on, the methodology of this paper is based on qualitative analysis of primary and"
"secondary sources on security sector reform, state-building and reconstruction programs."
This research  is structured  into two major parts. Part  1 provides theoretical  and analytical
framework  of  SSR  concept.  Chapter  1 traces  diverse  political  and  ideological  origins  of security  sector  reform  in  security-development  discourse  after  the  end  of  Cold  War.  lt
examines how the change of the very meaning of security and liberal ideas of  1990s have
"influenced the concept formation and fated its shortcomings. Chapter II aims to suit SSR within state-building paradigm, the integral part of which SSR has now become; and to explain some of its operational contradictions. Chapter III focuses on the orthodox  SSR model and summarizes its basic principles and norms. Part 2 provides an empirical analysis and demonstrates how the theoretical prepositions of SSR have been implemented on the ground. Chapter IV details historical process of statehood in Afghanistan and gives a portrait of the situation in the country prior to international intervention. Chapter V explores the implementation    of    SSR   along    four   main    pillars:    military,    police,   judicial    and"
counternarcoti es.
"The research  paper  contains two annexes, the first showing the World  Bank' s Worldwide"
"Governance Indicators, which measure the quality of governance in Afghanistan  during the period   of  international   donors'   engagement  in  reconstruction   process,   and  the  second"
summarizing the peacekeeping operations deployed by the United Nations.
lt is necessary to stress that current study does not attempt to map the tremendous assistance
"efforts,  provided  by  various  United  Nations  agencies  and  other  international  bodies  in Afghanistan,  and  concentrated  on  particular  donors'  activities  implemented  within  SSR"
paradigm.
Chapter 1.      Security-development   discourse  after  the  end  of  Cold  War:  roots  of
security sector reform
lntroduction
"The end  of the  Cold War, covering the period  from November  1989 with the fall  of the"
"Berlin Wall to December 1991 with the collapse of Communism and the downfall of the Soviet Union, aroused great hopes about prosperous and safe future and appeared to initiate a new era in international relations. However, the early 1990s have brought an obvious disconnect between the anticipated peace and spread of low-level armed and ethnic conflicts around the globe. While some countries managed to break into liberal-style democratisation process, most of the others plunged into violent crisis and stepped on the road towards state failure. Afghanistan , Angola, C6te d'Ivoire, East Timor, Sierra Leone, Somalia, Sudan, the Democratic Republic of the Congo - this is not the entire list of states, which  got  into growing dependence upon international assistance and economic  aid. Moreover, the forty­ five years of the Long Peace (Gaddis 1986:  142) have  created fragile but balanced world order system (Sheehan 1996: 171-172), with clear political and ideological  difference between rival blocks, when threats could easily be described within 'national security - national insecurity' frame. A sharp transition from predictable bipolar system  to unpredictable  new reality has profoundly  changed the concept of security and facilitated  a"
new thinking on security-development  assistance.
This chapter provides an overview of theoretical discussions in security-development  agenda
"since the end of Cold War confrontation. lt maps out diverse origins of this discourse and explores its impact on the emergence of security sector reform concept. Section 1 outlines development of the notion of security within the following main paradigms: (1) Realism , (2) Copenhagen School of security studies, namely Barry Buzan's concept of security,  (3) Critical Security Studies, and (4) Human Security. lt shows the evolvement of security definition and its conceptual and practical application. Section II explores the widening  of development agenda, and explains its convergence with security-related issues. Section III gives brief examination of the liberal peace of 1990s and its affection on the formation of new policy constructions. Section IV demonstrates how growing instability and conflicts created  conditions  for  complex  peace  operations,  which  incorporated  both  security  and"
development objectives.
1.         Redefinition of security: from realism to human security
1.1. Realist school of thought
"In the  aftermath  of World  War  II, the Realist  school  of thought  exercised  a hegemonic"
"position in the field of international relations, denouncing the notion of Idealism and promising to 'provide more accurate, more powerful , and more relevant answers to the questions of peace and war' (Brecher and Harvey 2002: 82). Orientation and direction of the superpowers in the international arena have been constructed through the realist paradigm , prioritizing the questions  of security, defence, and military  capacities necessary to address"
perceived or real outside threats.
Theoretical tradition of political realism has its roots in the works of Thucydides  (c. 460-c.
"400 BC), Niccolo Machiavelli (1469 - 1527) and Thomas Hobbes (1588 - 1679), which first referred to conflictual and competitive side of international politics. However, as a theory of international affairs it has been methodologically developed in XX centaury and associated mostly with such theorists as Hans Morgenthau (1904 - 1980), Edward Carr (1892 -1982), Kenneth Waltz (1924 -2013), and Robert Gilpin (1930 -2018). Although the realist  school has with the time evolved into classical realism, neorealism/structural  realism  and neoclassical realism theories, the cross-cutting concepts of those three approaches can be defined   in  the   set  of  terms,  namely,  nation-state,  military   power,  national   security,"
"international anarchy, balance of power, security dilemma and some others."
"According  to  all  realists, the  state is the  main  actor  on the  international  scene  and  any"
"significant actions, as well as foreign policy can only be conducted by the states. But if orthodox realists addressed to the great powers only, other representatives of the school recognized the importance of non-governmental actors, inter alia, international intergovernmental and non-profit organizations, along with pre-eminent role of the nation­ states. Second, the state was defined as a unitary and rational entity, which pursues a foreign policy that ensures its dominant position in international diplomatic  arena,  expands  the sphere of influence, as well as protects national interests and security. The realist conception of the state assumes that any sovereign country seeks to shape the  context  of  political process to its advantage and since all other states are equally involved in active struggle for power and political influence, it eventually results in competition among states. This competition is a direct consequence of international anarchy, in which international relations"
are  conducted.  International  anarchy  can  be  understood   as  a  structural  condition  of
international political system that is characterized  by the absence of an overall coordination
"mechanism to introduce common international regulations , rules or standards for actors involved. However, 'anarchy does not mean chaos. lt is, rather, the literal Greek meaning of the lack of governance.  States are sovereign and, by definition, no authority resides above"
them' (Holsti 1996: 7).
"In other words, no global power or single control centre over international relations exists to"
"enforce peace among nation-states. As a result, of the primary concern for any state is the protection of national security, the only viable option to guarantee which is military power. The realists assumed that smaller states might ensure their survival and security in a multipolar international system through alliances with larger powers (Gärtner et al. 2001: 2), while for the great powers, the key mechanism to address security has been seen in the balance of power. The balance of power can be defined as equilibrium or stability among the nations-states in terms of equal military capabilities, which are essential to maintain and preserve one's own political independence and to protect one's interests. However, the other side of the coin is the security dilemma, a situation when one state begins to increase its military potential for fear of aggression, what in turn leads to the retaliatory measures taken by  other  actors  to  restore  the  balance.  John  Herz  developed  the  following  definition  of"
security dilemma:
A structural notion in which the self-help attempts of states to look after their security
"needs  tend,  regardless  of  intention,  to  lead  to  rising  insecurity  for  others  as  each interprets  its  own  measures  as  defensive  and  measures  of  others  as  potentially"
threatening (Herz 1950: 157).
"During the Cold War and the nuclear arms race, the world has faced the permanent  state of"
"security dilemma and the balance of power game played by the Soviet Union and the United States. The military security agenda of both countries has overshadowed all other policies and values, justifying such actions as necessary to protect its sovereign territories and population against the threat from the West or the East respectively. Security was therefore understood as state-centric and military-centric concept, the central preposition of which was the state, while rights and security of individuals have been easily marginalized in favour of national  security goals. The working definition  of security has been limited to (1) national"
"security, (2) protection of national interests, and (3) security from nuclear war."
1.2. Barry Buzan and widening of security agenda
The first attempt to broaden security concept has been taken by Barry Buzan (born 1946) in
"his book 'People, States and Fear: The National Security Problem in International Relations ', published in 1983. Buzan 's analysis can be classified under the neorealist theory as he accepts that 'the international political system is an anarchy, which is to say that its principal defining characteristic is the absence of overarching government. The principal defining feature of state is their sovereignty or their refusal to acknowledge any political authority higher than themselves ' (Buzan 2007: 128). However, he has criticized the traditional interpretation of security as 'too narrowly founded ' (Buzan 2007: 34) and has developed a fundamentally new approach to security studies. Buzan moved beyond the realist' s preoccupation with security as exclusively military concern, and has expended the concept horizontally by adding four more sectors of potential  national  security threats,"
"namely, political , economic, societal, and ecological."
"Military threats maintained the central position in national security agenda, since any foreign"
"military intervention in any  form might threaten the very existence of the state. Military actions constitute the biggest <langer to the preservation of nations' territorial integrity, to the well-functioning of its political institutions, industrial structures, as well as to the state's cultural heritage, and interests of society and individuals at large. Buzan has identified two types of military threats, namely, direct and indirect. Direct threats come from foreign armed forces' invasion or attack on the country, military occupation of territories or bombardment of the cities, while indirect threats manifest in the form of attacks on allies, routs of strategic"
"significance, or shipping lanes, in another words, they affects the state's external interests."
"Political threats are more ambiguous by its very nature, and therefore they are more difficult"
"to define in comparison to military ones. Such threats might be transformed into imposition of sanctions and pressure over the leadership, subversive activities aimed at national identity decay, weakening of the national ideology or awakening racial or sectarian tensions. These measures are directed to undermine organisational  stability and political  order of the state,"
setting the ground for military attack.
Societal  threats  are  intertwined  with  political  ones  smce  they  focus  on  deterioration  of
"national  sentiment' s sustainability , language, cultural traditions and customs or religion and"
"values.  The  imposition  of  American  lifestyle  or  penetration   of  Western  ideas  can  be considered by individual  Islamic countries as societal threats. However, such concerns are"
"not necessarily  a direct result of the outside interference, but  of the state itself. As Buzan"
"pointed out 'it is one of the awful contradictions of national security logic that the suppression of sub-national identities might well contribute, in the long run, to the creation of stronger and more viable states' (Buzan 2007: 112). Oppressive practices against  the women and imposition of the strict Sharia law under the Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan regime (The Taliban rule) can undoubtedly be considered as the societal threat towards own"
population.
"With  regard  to  economic  threats,  it  is  often  difficult  to  disentangle  which  concems  are"
"directly attributable to normal functioning of market economy, and which may be considered as the threats to national security. Economic threats can manifest themselves in a variety of forms, ranging from the vulnerability of the state to the global financial crisis and possible collapse of its financial institutions, to economic sanctions or restrictions , and trade price manipulations.  Since military capability of the state rests on its economic development and"
"strength, these two sectors are largely interdependent."
The last sector of Buzan's analysis is devoted to ecological issues. For most of the twentieth
"century, environment has been a marginal policy area for the international community. Ecological disasters have been seen rather as a struggle of human beings with the Mother Nature, than as national threat. In the late 1980s, visibility of negative effects of human activity on the environment has triggered the growth of environmental awareness and development of first legal provisions in the field of ecology. Chemical and nuclear pollution, stratospheric ozone depletion, or scarcity of freshwater have been recognised  as the sources"
"of threat to human security, and therefore to national security."
"According to Buzan, 'these five sectors do not  operate in isolation  from  each other. Each"
"defines a focal point within the security problematique , and a way of ordering priorities , but all are woven together in a strong web of linkage' (Buzan 199la: 433). Since some of these threats are transnational in nature and can affect not only a single country, but neighbouring ones, Buzan has widened security definition vertically by addressing it on national , regional , and international  levels. He acknowledged that national security should be considered in a context 'of security interdependence in which it is embedded' (Buzan 2007: 157), in other words geographical proximity has a role to play on the security dynamics among the states. Whether  it is share borders, historical  bonds  or ethnically  related  populations, the context"
"might  vary  from  positive  to  negative,  as well  as the  relations  between  the  states  might"
"represent the spectrum from friendship to distrust. In this regard, Buzan has introduced the"
"concept of security complex, which he defined as 'a group of states whose primary security concerns link together sufficiently closely that their national securities cannot realistically be"
considered apart from one another' (Buzan 2007: 160).
"However, despite broadening the security agenda, Buzan still considered state as a dominant"
"actor in international political system, as well as in the security dynamics between regional and international levels. In his understanding, the state is an essential security provider, and it remains therefore the referent object for security analysis. Accordingly, individual security is an important sub-structure of national and international  security, but it does not constitute"
"the bedrock. In this regard, Buzan proposed the following working definition of security:"
Security is taken to be about the pursuit of freedom from threat and the ability of states
"and societies to maintain their independent identity and their functional  integrity against forces of change, which they see as hostile. The bottom line of security is survival,  but  it  also  reasonably  includes  a  substantial  range  of  concerns  about  the"
conditions of existence (Buzan 1991: 432).
1.3. Critical security studies and shifting to individual security
"The reformation movement started in 1985 under the leadership of Mikhail Gorbachev, more"
"known as Perestroika, and the following dissolution of the Soviet Union and consequent end of the Cold War, have opened new avenues and thinking space when addressing the issues of security studies. The failure of political realism created  conditions  for  intellectual discussions, debates and disputes in the field of international relations over the questions on security. In 1994, the term 'critical security study' has been coined by the conference held at the York University in Toronto and enjoyed widespread attention in the discipline ever since. However, no agreement exists thus far on whether critical security study is an umbrella label for different approaches critical to the realist' s orthodox view on security, or it is a distinctive project that aims to develop 'a new, emancipation-oriented  paradigm  for  the theory and practice of security' (Wyn Jones 1999: 5). The main objects  of the  critical security discourse have been seen in providing changes to the social organisation and in bringing a new alternative order that extends community beyond nation-state paradigm. In particular, critical theorists seek to reorganise and improve society of the present, 'so that future social organisation frees those presently oppressed by the operation of the world as we"
"find it' (Mutimer 2012: 45). In other words, emancipation  has been placed  at the centre of"
"analysis. Ken Booth, a leading figure in the post-Marxist tradition of critical security theory,"
has argued that:
security  means  the  absence  of  threats.  Emancipation  is  the  freeing  of  people  (as
"individuals and groups) from those physical and human constraints which stop them carrying out what they would freely choose to do. War and threat of war is one of those constraints, together with poverty, poor education, political  oppression  and  so on.  Security  and  emancipation  are  two  sides  of  the  same  coin.  Emancipation ,  not"
power or order produces true security (Booth 1991: 319).
"Thus, the  referent  object  of  security  has  been  shifted  from  the  state  to  the  individuals,"
"acknowledging that human security must take precedence over all other concerns. States, in Booth's view, are important actors in world's politics, but they are 'unreliable, illogical and too diverse  in their character to use as the primary referent objects for a comprehensive theory of security' (1991: 320). In this regard, Bill McSweeney pointed  out that  'security must make sense at the basic level of the individual human being for it to make sense at the international level' (1999: 16). Furthermore, at the heart of emancipation lies the belief that 'my freedom depends on your freedom' (Booth 1991: 322), which broke down the barriers between foreign and national policy and brought gender, class and racial issues in critical security agenda. This paradigm 'emphasizes the role of both non-state actors and the non­ military dimension of security; and identifies security in the wider social, economic, environmental , and political goals' (Gärtner et al. 2001: 31). Critical security studies have significantly broadened understanding and perception  of security and created the foundation"
for the emergence of human security paradigm.
1.4. Human security
Long-standing dissatisfaction of critical scholars with traditional approach to security studies
"and formation of a new architecture of international relations with a wide range of governmental , transnational and non-state actors resulted in further development of security concept. The globalization era with its technological advances and the revolution in communications  has  not  only  facilitated  the  crossborder  cooperation  among  nations, but"
provoked emergence of new non-traditional and transnational security threats.
"In 1992, the United Nations Security Council has convened very first meeting at the level of"
"Heads of State and Government, at which it has been recognised that 'the absence of war and"
military  conflicts amongst states does not in itself ensure international  peace  and  security.
"[...] non-military sources of instability in the economic, social, humanitarian and ecological fields have become threats to peace and security' (S/23500, 1992). In line with the outcomes of this high-level summit, the UN Secretary-General Boutros Boutros-Ghali has released 'An Agenda for Peace: Preventive diplomacy, peacemaking and peace-keeping ', a report on conflict prevention in the post-Cold War world. An Agenda for Peace was the first international document that has grasped the changing context of transitional period and identified new dimensions of insecurity. Climate change, poverty , famine, diseases, as well as growing inequality between the world's rich and poor, gender inequality, drug trafficking were for the first time acknowledged as both sources and triggers of conflicts and violence. This brand new understanding of multilayered nature of insecurity has resulted in the reassessment of previous security definitions and extension of its approaches beyond traditional interpretation. In 1994, an introduction of the United Nations Human Development Report (HDR) undoubtedly represented a serious breakthrough in recognition of the importance of human security over state-centred security: individuals, groups and communities, rather than the state, have been placed at the core of security scope with a"
"greater focus on people' s empowerment , dignity and protection."
Human security in its broadest  sense embraces far more than the absence of violent
"conflict. lt encompasses human rights, good governance, access to education  and health care, and ensuring that each individual has opportunities and choices to fulfil his or her own potential. Freedom from want, freedom from fear and the freedom of the future generations to inherit a healthy natural  environment - these are the interrelated"
"building blocks of human and therefore national security (SG/ SM/7382, 2000)."
The basic  assumption  of human  security was that if people perceive  threats to their basic
"needs (whether unemployment , natural disaster, crime, repressions , social conflict or other daily-life security concerns), they endure suffering, what could directly or indirectly trigger social or structural violence. Similarly, the states where human security is protected and the right of individuals are guaranteed are less likely to experience conflicts of different types. Human security encompasses therefore two main components: 'freedom from fear' , i.e. protection of people from armed conflicts and related threats; and 'freedom from want' , i.e. protection  of  people  from  natural  disasters,  diseases,  hunger  and  other  threats  beyond"
violence approach. A total of seven categories of human security have been identified by the
"1994  HDR   (see  Table   1),  namely   econom1c   security,  food   security,  health   security,"
"environmental security, personal security, community security, and political security."
Table 1: Dimensions  of human security according to 1994 Human development report
Economic security            Health security                  Environmental
security
Personal security
Provision of stable and
guaranteed  income through remunerative work
Access to quality health
"care, protection from diseases, opportunity  to live healthy lifestyle"
Protection from natural
"disasters, or man-made environmental degradation"
Protection from physical
"violence, posed by the state or other states, from violent groups of individuals, from domestic abuse or from self­ destruction (suicide,"
                                                                                                                                          narcotic dmgs consumption)    
Food security                      Community security        Political security
Both physical and
economical access to basic food
Protection of traditional
"cultures, relationships and values"
Ensuring guarantee and
respect of human rights in society
"Source:  UNDP Human Development Report,  1994, 24-25."
"In the context of human security concept, economic security means a guaranteed income for"
"everyone through the productive employment and decent work, or at least through the government funding. Individuals should enjoy the right to free access to the employment market, secure working conditions and decent salary. In this regard, the purchasing power of wages must provide food security, i.e. physical and economic access  to  sufficient  food. People should have an opportunity to purchase food items, to grow their own food products, or to take advantage of foodbased safety net programmes. Health security stands for protection of civilians from diseases and unhealthy lifestyles, as well as for provision of quality healthcare, accessible to all segments of the population. Health-related problems of water scarcity, desertification, deforestation, air pollution and many others build up an environmental  component of human security. Environmental  security aims to protect people"
"from ecological disasters, both natural and human-made."
"Personal  security  represents  protection  of  individuals  from  physical  violence,  inter  alia,"
"threats emanating from the government or aggressive states, from violent individuals or criminal groups, including domestic abuse, child abuse or suicide attempts. Community security is about preserving the cultural traditions and values of  racial or ethnic groups, minorities and communities, and protection of them against direct (ethnic cleansings or genocide) and indirect (loss of language, cultural elements or customs) threats. The last category is political  security: individuals should enjoy the opportunity to live in society that"
"respects fundamental rights, freedoms and human dignity."
